Austin M. Putz – Curriculum Vitae

Personal Information Austin M. Putz 231 Kildee Hall Iowa State University Ames, IA 50010 Cell: 515-249-6638

Emails: aputz@iastate.edu | putz.austin@gmail.com

Links: LinkedIn | ResearchGate | GitHub

Summary:

I grew up on a diversified family farm in southern Iowa. During that time I gained experience with swine, beef, chickens, sheep, goats, and row crops. I've had positions at three different genetics labs as an undergrad at Iowa State. I've also taken three internships: Fast Genetics (on farm), Smithfield Premium Genetics (SPG) in R&D, and The Maschhoffs as a geneticist on special projects. This has provided me with valuable experience to see real world breeding programs. I have gained numerous technical skills gained during my M.S. and Ph.D. Includes R, Linux, bash scripting, vim, LATEX, Julia, ASReml, SAS, and SQL. My Master's was completed at North Carolina State University with SPG on a novel litter size trait. I'm currently a Ph.D. student with Dr. Jack Dekkers at Iowa State University working on disease resistance in both sow herds and wean-to-finish pigs.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Animal Breeding and Genetics from Iowa State University (2015-2018(expected)). Minor: Statistics

Committee: Jack C. M. Dekkers (PI), K. Stalder, A. Wolc, J. Cunnick, P. Dixon

Project on disease resistance in swine.

GPA: 3.78

M.S. degree in Animal Science from North Carolina State University

(2013-2015). Minor: Statistics

Committee: Mark Knauer (PI), K. A. Gray, C. Maltecca, H. Bondell

Thesis title: Alternative Litter Size Traits to Increase the Number of Weaned Pigs

in Swine. Thesis

GPA: 4.0

B.S. degree in Animal Science from Iowa State University (2009-2013).

GPA: 3.93 (Summa Cum Laude)

Computer skills

Programming/scripting languages Advanced: R, Bash scripting

Intermediate/Beginner: Julia, Python (3)

Genetic Software BLUPF90, ASReml, DMU (some), GenSel, JWAS (Julia)

Reporting LATEX(e.g. this CV), Shiny Apps

Operating systems Extensive experience with Mac OS. Solid experience with Ubuntu (Debian). Some experience with Windows.

Servers Successfully set up a home server (Ubuntu 16.04.1) to run genetic analyses (ssh, GenSel, BLUPF90, ASReml, R, Julia)

Databases Basic experience with SQL (SQLite)

Other GitHub, vim/awk/sed, SAS (modeling)

Open source projects Provide much of my code and help files through GitHub https://github.com/austin-putz

Work Experience

2015 - Intern Geneticist (Carlyle, IL) The Maschhoffs

Two special projects were completed. The first was looking into structural characteristics scored at off-test. The second was to develop code to evaluate and compare different farms.

- 2013 R&D Intern (Rose Hill, NC) Smithfield Premium Genetics Worked with SPG for my Master's degree in litter size. Helped them with a growth curve study and with collecting data at the packing plant for their evaluation program.
- 2012-2013 Swine Molecular Genetics (Ames, ISU) Dr. Chris Tuggle My first project was to prepare RNAseq samples from the RFI population. My second project was to develop an assay to genotype pigs for a large QTL for PRRS resistance at the *causative* locus.
- **2012 Breeding & Farrowing Tech** (Cando, North Dakota) Fast Genetics Spent a summer on a 6,000 head multiplier for Fast Genetics (HyLife). Was able to spend half of my time in breeding and half in farrowing. Also visited the nursery, finisher, and feed mill.
- 2012 Beef Genetics Lab (Ames, ISU), Dr. James Reecy Assisted Dr. Reecy's lab in data collaction on farm and running assays in the lab.
- 2011 Soil Microbiology Lab (Ames, ISU), Dr. Kirsten Hofmockel Helped with a lot of data collection in the field for many of the graduate projects in the summer. Then helped analyse and phenotype the samples that fall.

2010-2011 - Barn Crew Member (Ames, ISU) ISU Vet School

Teaching

Animal Breeding (undergrad) TA Spring 2017 under Dr. Bundy. Responsible for 1 lab section.

Swine Systems Management TA Fall 2016 under Dr. Stalder

Reproductive Physiology TA 2 semesters at NCSU

Organic Chemistry Tutor Spring 2012

Projects

All available on GitHub https://github.com/austin-putz

BLUPF90 wrapper Linux/Unix wrapper for BLUPF90 programs (many analyses)

BLUPF90 man pages man pages (Linux/Unix) for most BLUPF90 family of programs

vim syntax highlighting vim syntax highlighting for QMsim and BLUPF90

Honors & Awards

2016 Lauren L. Christian Graduate Fellowship (Dept AnS)

2016 Caine-Bogle Family Graduate Fellowship (CALS)

2015 Miller Graduate Fellowship (ISU)

2013 National Pork Board Scholarship

2012 Kenneth and Ruth Wagner Scholarship

2012 Arthur Molln Scholarship

2011 Lane Wells Scholarship

Publications

Putz, A. M., K. A. Gray, C. Maltecca, F. Tiezzi, and M. T. Knauer, A comparison of accuracy validation methods for genomic and pedigree based predictions of swine litter size traits in Large White and Landrace breeds, J. Anim. Sci (submitted)

Putz, A. M., K. A. Gray, C. Maltecca, F. Tiezzi, and M. T. Knauer, *Variance component estimates for alternative litter size traits in swine*, J. Anim. Sci 93 (2015). doi:10.2527/jas2015-9416 https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26641035

Abstracts

Putz, A. M., J. C. S. Harding, F. Fortin, G. S. Plastow, and J. C. M. Dekkers, *A natural challenge model for disease resilience in wean-to-finish pigs*, (2017) Presented orally at ASAS Midwestern Section.

Powell, E. J., A. M. Putz, A. Boettcher, L. Varley, J. E. Cunnick, M. Sauer, M. Schroyen, S. Charley, C. K. Tuggle, Contact hypersensitivity testing shows long-term hapten-specific memory associated with increased liver NK cell populations up to 32 days post-sensitization, (2016) Presented Autumn Immunology Conference.

Putz, A. M., C. R. Schwab, A. D. Sewell, and J. C. M. Dekkers, *The effect of PRRS virus disesase outbreak on genetic parameters of reproductive performance in pigs*, (2016) Presented with poster at ICQG.

Putz, A. M., K. A. Gray, C. Maltecca, F. Tiezzi, and M. T. Knauer, Accuracies of genomic and pedigree based predictions for swine litter size traits in Large White and Landrace breeds, (2015) Presented orally at ASAS Midwestern Section.

Putz, A. M., K. A. Gray, C. Maltecca, F. Tiezzi, and M. T. Knauer, *Variance component estimates for alternative litter size and piglet mortality traits*, (2014) Presented orally at ASAS Midwestern Section.

SHORT COURSES

Programming and computer algorithms in animal breeding with focus on genomic selection and single-step GBLUP, (2014) University of Georgia

References

Jack C. M. Dekkers Distinguished Professor, ISU jdekkers@iastate.edu 515-294-7509

Mark Knauer Assistant Professor, NCSU mtknauer@ncsu.edu 919-515-8797 Clint Schwab Director of Genetics, The Maschhoffs clint.schwab@pigsrus.net 618-335-6386

Kent Gray Head of R&D, Smithfield Premium Genetics (SPG) kent.gray@spgenetics.com 910-282-4227

Chris Tuggle Professor, ISU cktuggle@iastate.edu 515-294-4252